<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Terminal</title>
    <link>https://cglavin50.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Terminal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2023 15:05:27 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cglavin50.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Hugo!</title>
      <link>https://cglavin50.github.io/posts/myfirstpost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2023 15:05:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cglavin50.github.io/posts/myfirstpost/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m still learning Hugo, so these are some notes before I forget how to deploy a new post. First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m hosting everything in my &amp;ldquo;blog&amp;rdquo; github repo, however the deployment is the actual GitHub pages repo. I&amp;rsquo;ve linked the pages repo as a submodule, so after running &amp;ldquo;hugo -t terminal&amp;rdquo;, the content will compile into the public folder, pushing it from the blog to the actual site (will likely schedule a chron job for commits every night).</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still learning Hugo, so these are some notes before I forget how to deploy a new post. First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m hosting everything in my &amp;ldquo;blog&amp;rdquo; github repo, however the deployment is the actual GitHub pages repo. I&amp;rsquo;ve linked the pages repo as a submodule, so after running &amp;ldquo;hugo -t terminal&amp;rdquo;, the content will compile into the public folder, pushing it from the blog to the actual site (will likely schedule a chron job for commits every night). I locally installed the theme, so won&amp;rsquo;t worry about updating that (recommendation course of action is through Github actions). As for now, the to do list is to keep exploring with Hugo, and write the about page as well as a formal first post tonight to summarize everything I&amp;rsquo;ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://cglavin50.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cglavin50.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Who am I? I am an undergraduate at Georgetown University, pursuing a B.S. in Computer Science, and a minor in Mathematics, graduating in May 2024. Passionate about problem-solving, networking, and developing an easy-access internet for all, I love to learn and am always looking to find new tech to dive into.
What do I do? I am currently involved with anti-censorship research involving new network protocols on campus, and am a backend developer who enjoys learning web-dev on the side.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;who-am-i&#34;&gt;Who am I?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an undergraduate at Georgetown University, pursuing a B.S. in Computer Science, and a minor in Mathematics, graduating in May 2024. Passionate about problem-solving, networking, and developing an easy-access internet for all, I love to learn and am always looking to find new tech to dive into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-i-do&#34;&gt;What do I do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently involved with anti-censorship research involving new network protocols on campus, and am a backend developer who enjoys learning web-dev on the side. I love to code, and have been diving into Go recently as my language of choice, however am also interested in deployments and devops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I love to learn, I wanted to create this page as a blog post, where I intend to write one article covering something new I learned, every day. That way, I hold myself accountable, and I can use this as a place to refer back to when I want to build off something I remember from a previous review day.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
